<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://lasttalon.github.io/sentinel/blog</id>
    <title>Sentinel Blog</title>
    <updated>2023-06-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://lasttalon.github.io/sentinel/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Sentinel Blog</subtitle>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[In a Journey of a Thousand Miles]]></title>
        <id>https://lasttalon.github.io/sentinel/blog/a-thousand-miles</id>
        <link href="https://lasttalon.github.io/sentinel/blog/a-thousand-miles"/>
        <updated>2023-06-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome back, friend.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back, friend.</p><p>A week ago, I embarked on a new chapter in the development of Sentinel, inviting
you all to join me as I live-stream the entire process. This decision, driven by
a philosophy of "developing in the open", has transformed game development into
a shared adventure, complete with its ups, downs, and everything in between.</p><p>The streams have provided an opportunity not just to watch code take shape, but
also to delve into the journey behind it — the planning, the challenges, the
breakthroughs, and the continuous refining of our project.</p><p>For more on the philosophy that inspired this journey and the initial steps we
took together, I invite you to revisit <a href="/sentinel/blog/broadcast-intercepted">my
announcement</a> from last week. Now, let's
reflect on our first week's milestones and look ahead to what's coming.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="celebrating-progress">Celebrating Progress<a href="#celebrating-progress" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Celebrating Progress" title="Direct link to Celebrating Progress">​</a></h2><p>Since the launch, we've accomplished an exciting number of milestones. With
three successful streams under our belt and the fourth happening tonight, we're
steadily creating a space for transparency, learning, and communal development.</p><p>Our follower count has been steadily rising and I am humbled by the response
we've been receiving. The progress is palpable and we're moving ever closer to
our goal of becoming a Twitch Affiliate. The only requirement left is to
continue streaming and that's exactly what we plan to do.</p><p>Community engagement has been nothing short of phenomenal. Every stream feels
like a dialogue — a genuine conversation with those who have become as invested
in the development of Sentinel as I am. Every question, every suggestion, every
shared laugh — it all contributes to an atmosphere of collective creativity and
camaraderie. I can't wait to engage with all of you every time I go live.</p><p>Finally, I want to acknowledge the personal growth that this journey has
stimulated. Being on camera, narrating my process and my thoughts, engaging with
the community — it's been a learning curve. It's an aspect of the process I
continue to adapt to and improve upon, but I am embracing the challenge and am
eager to evolve alongside Sentinel.</p><p>These achievements are not just mine, but ours as a community. Here's to many
more milestones ahead!</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="turning-obstacles-into-opportunities">Turning Obstacles into Opportunities<a href="#turning-obstacles-into-opportunities" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Turning Obstacles into Opportunities" title="Direct link to Turning Obstacles into Opportunities">​</a></h2><p>This journey has brought with it its fair share of obstacles, but each of these
challenges has been an opportunity for growth and learning.</p><p>Our maiden stream was a crash course in adapting on the fly. We encountered a
few technical problems, but rather than getting bogged down, we used this as a
chance to demonstrate real-world problem-solving. It was an unexpected
opportunity to showcase the less glamorous, yet equally important, aspects of
development — troubleshooting and resilience.</p><p>Balancing time and energy among various commitments has been another significant
challenge. Aligning streaming times, development hours, and personal commitments
is not an easy task. But this has spurred me towards a more mindful approach to
scheduling and the prioritization of tasks. I'm continually learning how to
better manage my time to create a harmonious balance that benefits everyone,
myself included.</p><p>Unfortunately, health reasons led to the cancellation of one of our streams.
However, the understanding and support I received from all of you was
overwhelming and incredibly heartening. It served as a reminder of the
importance of taking care of oneself and how integral rest is to the creative
process. We resumed right where we left off, and this only strengthened our
resolve to continue this exciting journey.</p><p>These obstacles have not been setbacks, but stepping stones towards bettering
myself and improving the live stream experience for all of you.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="whats-on-the-horizon">What's on the Horizon<a href="#whats-on-the-horizon" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What's on the Horizon" title="Direct link to What's on the Horizon">​</a></h2><p>As we continue, our immediate focus is to continue pushing forward towards
completing our minimum core gameplay loop for Sentinel.</p><p>For those unfamiliar with game development jargon, a "core gameplay loop" refers
to the primary sequence of activities a player does repeatedly — in essence, the
main actions and interactions that define the game. Establishing this
fundamental structure allows us to have a solid foundation upon which we can
then iterate, refine and expand.</p><p>Iterating on the core gameplay loop is where the magic happens — this is when
we'll test, tweak, and refine elements of the game, from balance and pacing to
player engagement and satisfaction. Each iteration gives us the chance to
improve Sentinel, ensuring it's not just functional, but also fun, immersive and
compelling.</p><p>While it's hard to provide specifics at this stage without spoiling the
surprise, you can expect continued development in various game mechanics, AI
behaviors, level design, player abilities and more. I'm eager to tackle these
areas in upcoming streams and engage you all in the process.</p><p>This is just the start of our journey, and there's so much more to look forward
to. I hope you're as excited about the future of Sentinel as I am!</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="striking-the-balance-organizing-time-for-better-harmony">Striking the Balance: Organizing Time for Better Harmony<a href="#striking-the-balance-organizing-time-for-better-harmony" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Striking the Balance: Organizing Time for Better Harmony" title="Direct link to Striking the Balance: Organizing Time for Better Harmony">​</a></h2><p>Life, like any good game, is about balance. The way we manage our time,
distribute our energy, and align our priorities forms a complex, evolving
equilibrium that influences our overall well-being and effectiveness. Many call
this "work-life balance", but I prefer to think of it as "life equilibrium" or
"time harmony".</p><p>The term "work-life balance" suggests an inherent opposition between work and
life — as though work isn't a part of our lives, but rather something that takes
away from it. This viewpoint can foster a sense of tension and dissatisfaction,
as we may feel that our work hours are somehow 'lost' or 'wasted' time. In
contrast, the concepts of "life equilibrium" and "time harmony" offer a
healthier, more holistic perspective. They acknowledge that work is indeed a
part of our lives, and emphasize the importance of distributing our time in ways
that enable us to live fully and authentically.</p><p>In this spirit, I've decided to adjust my streaming and work schedule. The new
schedule not only accommodates my various commitments, but also aligns with my
natural rhythms and preferences for focus and rest. I believe it will allow me
to bring you more engaging, energetic streams, without compromising my other
responsibilities or my personal well-being.</p><p>Here's what the new schedule looks like:</p><ul><li><strong>Monday:</strong> Stream at 1 PM CT / 6 PM UTC</li><li><strong>Tuesday:</strong> Stream at 1 PM CT / 6 PM UTC</li><li><strong>Wednesday:</strong> No stream. New blog post published.</li><li><strong>Thursday:</strong> Day off.</li><li><strong>Friday:</strong> Stream at 1 PM CT / 6 PM UTC</li><li><strong>Saturday:</strong> Stream at 1 PM CT / 6 PM UTC</li><li><strong>Sunday:</strong> No stream. New highlights video published.</li></ul><p>I invite you all to join me as I navigate this new schedule. Your support and
engagement in the live streams is not just appreciated — it's invaluable. You
can get notified about when I go live by following me on
<a href="https://www.twitch.tv/lasttalon" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Twitch</a>,
<a href="https://twitter.com/LastTalon" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Twitter</a>,
<a href="https://mastodon.gamedev.place/@LastTalon" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mastodon</a>, and
<a href="https://discord.gg/aq2UkZUWsj" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discord</a>. Let's continue to learn and grow
together!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Lucas Gangstad</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Broadcast Intercepted: Development Live Streams]]></title>
        <id>https://lasttalon.github.io/sentinel/blog/broadcast-intercepted</id>
        <link href="https://lasttalon.github.io/sentinel/blog/broadcast-intercepted"/>
        <updated>2023-06-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hello there, friend.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello there, friend.</p><p>If you've been following along with my project, <em>Sentinel</em>, you might be
interested to hear that I've decided to take things in a new direction. Starting
soon, I'll be live streaming my development process on <a href="https://www.twitch.tv/lasttalon" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Twitch</a>. This is a
journey I've been eager to embark on, and I'm genuinely thrilled to share it
with you. In this post, I'll let you in on what you can expect from these live
streams and why I believe this journey can be an enriching adventure for
everyone.</p><p>I am excited to reveal that starting from tomorrow, Tuesday, June 13th, I'll be
opening the doors of my development process, and you're invited to join me.
You'll get a front-row seat as I code, make design decisions, and tackle the
very real challenges that come with software development.</p><p>To skip to the stream invitation, <a href="#youre-invited">check below</a>.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="description-of-streaming-content">Description of Streaming Content<a href="#description-of-streaming-content" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Description of Streaming Content" title="Direct link to Description of Streaming Content">​</a></h2><p>These live streams provide a peek inside the code editor of a developer. They're
a shared journey, a platform to explore the multifaceted process of creating
<em>Sentinel</em>, a project that's very close to my heart. A development live stream
is an opportunity to watch a software project come to life in real-time. You'll
get to see everything: the code being written, problems being debugged, and
features being designed and implemented.</p><p>For those unfamiliar with the project, <em>Sentinel</em> is a cooperative, hero-based,
horde survival game. It's designed for the <em>Roblox</em> platform, targeting players
aged 12 and above who seek a more mature, thrilling gaming experience. Drawing
inspiration from popular games like <em>Dota</em> and horde survival games like
<em>Killing Floor</em> or <em>Left 4 Dead</em>, <em>Sentinel</em> is packed with exciting game modes,
challenging boss battles, and a robust progression system. I genuinely believe
it holds the potential to become a standout title on the <em>Roblox</em> platform.</p><p>But I want to give you more than just a front-row seat to coding. I want to
share the full breadth of the development journey with you. True development
goes beyond just writing software; it encompasses planning, iterating, refining,
and sometimes, starting from scratch. From setting up documentation and this
blog to managing our issue tracker, these streams will offer a holistic look
into the development process. It's about laying bare the realities of creating
something from scratch, warts and all, and I couldn't be more excited to share
it with you.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-reveal-my-secrets">Why Reveal My Secrets?<a href="#why-reveal-my-secrets" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why Reveal My Secrets?" title="Direct link to Why Reveal My Secrets?">​</a></h2><p>Why have I decided to broadcast my journey? There are several reasons, but they
all converge on a single value: openness. I am a strong believer in the
<a href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">philosophy</a> of "developing
in the open." This principle extends beyond just making the source code publicly
available. It encompasses sharing the thought processes, the struggles, the
eureka moments, the disappointments, and the victories that come with the
journey of software development. By exposing the entire lifecycle of a project,
we foster a sense of authenticity, allowing for a richer learning and
community-building experience.</p><p>These live streams are an extension of this belief, serving as a live
documentation of <em>Sentinel's</em> development process. My hope is that these
sessions provide a valuable educational resource, offering a first-hand look
into the nitty-gritty of developing a software project. It's a platform for
learning, but also an invitation to join the conversation, to share insights,
and to learn together. This transparency isn't just about my growth as a
developer, but also about helping each other grow, and learning from one
another's experiences.</p><p>And it's not just about learning. I believe that watching a project evolve,
engaging in the process, and experiencing the triumphs and challenges along the
way, also fosters a sense of camaraderie and community. I hope to make these
streams not just informative, but also an enjoyable space where we can connect
over shared passions and experiences.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="end-of-transmission">End of Transmission<a href="#end-of-transmission" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to End of Transmission" title="Direct link to End of Transmission">​</a></h2><p>Thank you all for your support and for sharing this journey with me. In these
streams, you're not just a spectator, but an integral part of the development
process. I look forward to learning, growing, and creating with you. Who knows
where this adventure will lead us?</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="youre-invited">You're Invited<a href="#youre-invited" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to You're Invited" title="Direct link to You're Invited">​</a></h2><p>I'd love for you to be a part of this journey with me. Here's how you can join
in:</p><p>Join me live on <a href="https://www.twitch.tv/lasttalon" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Twitch</a> for some thrilling <em>Sentinel</em> development sessions.
Mark your calendars for these dates (all times in Central Time (CT), and
Coordinated Universal Time (UTC)):</p><ul><li>Tuesday, June 13, 2023: 8:30 PM CT / 1:30 AM UTC (next day)</li><li>Wednesday, June 14, 2023: 8:30 PM CT / 1:30 AM UTC (next day)</li><li>Thursday, June 15, 2023: 8:30 PM CT / 1:30 AM UTC (next day)</li><li>Friday, June 16, 2023: 8:30 PM CT / 1:30 AM UTC (next day)</li><li>Saturday, June 17, 2023: 8:30 PM CT / 1:30 AM UTC (next day)</li></ul><p>Each stream will run for approximately 2-3 hours.</p><p>For an even more engaging experience, come join our <a href="https://discord.gg/aq2UkZUWsj" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discord</a> community. You'll
find all the latest updates, get the chance to discuss the development process,
and connect with fellow <em>Sentinel</em> enthusiasts.</p><p>And for more casual updates and interactions, you can find me on Twitter
<a href="https://twitter.com/LastTalon" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@LastTalon</a> and Mastodon
<a href="https://mastodon.gamedev.place/@LastTalon" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@LastTalon@mastodon.gamedev.place</a>.
Looking forward to connecting with you!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Lucas Gangstad</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>